Work Is Hard

Introduction

As a young person I was driven to succeed in education, because I thought it was the best way to not end up working a Burger King job. There’s a lot of things that I didn’t know as a young person, and knowing some of them much earlier would have made my life a lot easier. At the very least I would have been able to make my decisions more consciously, and I think that making decisions consciously makes it much easier to make good decisions that are hard, or that require constant maintenance. Letting “things just happen” seems to be the easiest way to end up in a world of hurt. That’s why I started writing this - so that kids from backgrounds where their parents can’t help them financially would have a reference for the things that they don’t need to learn the hard way.

About Poverty and Getting Out of It

Poverty means a lot of different things to a lot of people, but if you think you are in poverty, and want to get out, then you can do it with education. I don’t intend to confuse or mislead you though - education is not an easy route to make lots of money. I don’t know if there is any easy route out of poverty. But I know there is a slow and reliable route by learning all the things. I doubt you’ll become a moneybags through education, as that isn’t really the point. People like Bill Gates and Steve Jobs and so forth had to have some education, but it wasn’t education that made either of them rich. It was their work ethic, a lot of luck, and taking risks that happened to pay off for them.

I’m not going to recommend risky options to you. I might point some out as we identify them in discussing the long road. At any point you might find that there’s a risky shortcut you can take to get you out of poverty fast, and as you become more educated and build more contacts these will become more and more frequent possibilities. You can take one of these routes any time you want! But keep in mind when you do that it is easier to go from zero to hero that it is to go from negative a million dollars to a house and car.

Are you sure you even want to exit the poverty level for income? There are a lot of styles of life that don’t really require much that you can be happy with. Having a great and loving family, being an incredible artist, and living from couch to couch with your friends are all alternatives that may work for your personality type. Some people even prefer to live on a sailboat! Education is a slow path, and it isn’t right for everyone. Think about it.

When I think about “exiting poverty”, I imagine myself with a working car, being able to support my hobbies of computers and musical instruments, a living space that can support those hobbies, and being able to go out with my friends when I want. This is what middle class means for me, and I couldn’t have gotten there without an education. I hope that you will think about what it means for you, so that you know what kind of income you need to make to support the kind of lifestyle you want to live.

Anyone Can Go to College

I can’t tell you how many times people have told me that they “can’t afford to go to college.” The saddest part of it is that most of them actually believe it, and it is a bald-faced untruth.

Politicians like to bandy about phrases like “an education isn’t worth what it used to be”. Uneducated adults may try to tell you to look at people like Steve Jobs, who dropped out of college, started a business, and became a billionaire. Politicians do this because they want to draw attention away from the fact that higher education in the United States is massively underfunded compared to other nations, and convince voters that higher education isn’t worth spending on so they can put your tax dollars somewhere else. Adults are doing it simply because they want to convince themselves that they can still get rich even though they don’t have an education. When you look around, the cases where people actually manage to get out of poverty without either a whole lot of luck or a whole lot of work are few and far between. The simple fact is that if you are coming from poverty you almost always need to go to college.

Let’s actually take a look at Steve Jobs. He may not have gotten where he was just because of education, but the truth is that he had to use up a lot of luck to get where he did. Do you want to rely on luck to get out of poverty? Odds are that you won’t even have any funds to take risks with if you don’t get an education. A college education may not be the easy in to a good job that it once was, but not having a college education is an easy out of most good jobs. For every person like Steve Jobs who took massive risks and got massive reward, there are likely hundreds who took the massive risk and ended up living with their parents in the basement. But you? If you came from poverty your parents may not have a basement. They may be struggling to pay their rent, so how could they possibly feed and house you? It is your responsibility to plan your safety nets for your adult life, not theirs.

Some people will try to tell you that you can work your way up. They say that you can get a job at a fast food restaurant, save up, and then use that do [….some unspecified thing] that will help you get out of poverty. This is garbage.

If you are trying to get out of poverty using a minimum wage job, you are doing it wrong. You simply can’t make enough money to pay your rent, feed and clothe yourself, and save up much of anything. You certainly won’t be able to save up for college from a fast food job. Do you know how much a good college education costs in 2013? Really? Go google the cost of 4 years at Harvard right now.

Did you do it?

No?

I did. Today it says that a full year of costs at Harvard is nearly $63,000. So 4 years at Harvard will cost you $252,000. With a federal minimum wage of $7.25, that’s 34758 hours. With an average working year of 2086 hours, that is nearly 17 years working and taking nothing out of your paycheck to feed or clothe yourself, or to have a roof over your head. So no, you will never save up for Harvard at a minimum wage job. You will be dead before you can do it that way.

Why did I pick Harvard? Because the better the school you go to, the better the contacts you can make, the better your degree looks on your resume, and the more likely you’ll get a good job when you get out. Rich people know this, that’s why they send their kids to good schools. You think they just wanted to throw away money? It is about building as much opportunity for yourself as you can.

I’m not saying that online education isn’t good. I’m saying that if you need to get out of poverty, online education isn’t going to provide you the contacts or the instant prestige to get the job that you need to get to stay out of poverty. Once you already have contacts and prestige, please, go do online education. Learn as much as you can stuff in your brain! But until then, you need to go where the people are, and you need to go somewhere people think that you had to work hard to get a degree.

What about community college? Yes, you might be able to save up for a few years at community college if you scrimp and save for a long time. You may even be able to use community college to get a degree in something that is immediately valuable to your community, and get a job in it. You may be able to leave poverty this way, but I think it is not as reliable as a 4 year degree since the needs of a community constantly shift, and a very specific degree may be totally useless in a few years, and then you’ll be back where you were before you started, a few years older, and a few years more difficult to educate.

If you are already an adult, then community college is useful to you. You may want to use community college to get a transfer into a 4 year institution. We’ll talk more about how you might fund that transition in the next chapter.

How to Afford College

If you can’t save up enough money to go to college, then how can someone in poverty get there? So far I’ve seen and explored two ways: The hard way, and the risky way.

The Hard Way

This path will really only work if you haven’t started or are just starting high school. The earlier you start on this path, the better. The end goal of this path is to get a four year scholarship to a good school. You can do it, as I’ve done it and I’ve seen a lot of other people do it. Good schools want good students because good students become great researchers, and that brings them prestige. What makes a good student is the drive to succeed. You are driven to escape poverty, so you already have that drive. You just need to learn to focus it so that you can get what you want out of it.

How does a student get a 4 year scholarship? I think a lot of people would say that it is by being very brilliant or working very hard. I disagree. I think you can only get a 4 year scholarship if you work very, very hard. Most of the people who get labeled brilliant look brilliant because they started working very hard much earlier than their peers. People around brilliant people assume brilliant people just popped out of their mother that way. I don’t buy that for an instant, and you shouldn’t either, as it is just a bad excuse for not working hard. There are definitely environmental and genetic factors that influence whether or not you will be able to learn quickly, but people with great genetics and perfect environments often don’t thrive simply because they face no challenges that inspire them to become great.

You have that challenge. Use it wisely. Every time that someone makes fun of you for not having nice clothes, or the wrong shoes for the activity, you should be thinking internally how grateful you are that you have a challenge to succeed against. You should be grateful that you don’t have the money to spend on going to the movies with your friends, because it means that you have no excuse not to spend that time learning.

Throughout school you’ll make friends with some great teachers. This is because people like you are what inspire them. They are inspired by students who soak up knowledge with excitement and accept criticism without complaint because you know it makes you better. They enjoy students who join competitions and excel because it gives their life high points to find and help students who need and want it. That is usually why they took the job in the first place. When you find these great teachers, you should be incredibly grateful that you have the opportunity to work with them. You should listen to their advice, and request it for things that they might know about.

This is the hard way. It is hard because you need to plan each and every class according to the level of college you want to attend. You need to meet every prerequisite for that college level. You need to ace every class that you can, and always, always do your best. I can’t say precisely what GPA you need to have to get a 4 year scholarship, but I’d guess it is pretty close to a 4.0. That’s unweighted. If your school weights AP classes, you need to get As in every single class.

You’ll want to join competitions in areas that you excel in, preferably ones that take you out of your district so you can see if you really are a big fish in a small pond, or a medium fish in a small pond. It provides you a sense of scope, and will also likely help inspire what fields you might be interested in during college.

If you take The Hard Way, and you succeed at the college you get into with the hard way, you’ll have no debt coming out of college. This means you can pick whatever major you want, as in the worst case you finish university with a lot of knowledge and no debt. This assumes you finish successfully - and we’ll talk about what might cause that to not happen later.

The Risky Way

I call this the risky way because if you fail college having used this path, you may end up in a worse position than you started out in. Before you go to college, your parents may have no money, but you have no debt. If you go to college The Hard Way, you’ll leave college with no or very little debt. If you decide to go to college The Risky Way, you’ll leave with a whole lot of debt that you need to pay off with a reliable job. That means you need to mitigate the risk of that debt so that you don’t ruin your credit so early that you can never dig your way out to afford a house.

We discussed the cost of a Harvard education earlier. If you didn’t try The Hard Way at all, you likely won’t even be able to get in to Harvard, so you don’t have to worry about it costing that much. You’ll apply to a whole bunch of schools of varying levels. Some of them will have costs near Harvard, and at the lowest some may be near community college. Depending on the needs of the particular schools and your extracurricular activities, and the quality of your essays, you may get into some of the higher prestige schools.

Optimizing for opportunity at the college level means balancing university prestige with how much you’ll need to leverage that prestige when trying to get a job. This depends on your major. If you major in a field where there are many desirable jobs available, you won’t need to leverage the prestige of your university as much to get one of them. It also depends on how easily you can demonstrate the skills of your major in an interview. For many jobs, you cannot easily demonstrate the skills you learned in your major during the interview. Because of this, jobs of this sort rely more on the prestige of your education and the strength of your contacts, so you will want to plan to go to a higher prestige school so you can get the interview in the first place.

The problem is that the higher prestige universities have many more students applying, and thus find that they can charge a whole lot more. So you’ll have to decide your major by considering the level of risk that you want to accrue by gathering debt at an institution that teaches that major with high prestige. If you don’t want to take a lot of risk by taking huge debt, you may not want to choose a major that is not much sought after, or that is difficult to interview for.

The Fallback Plan

If you try The Hard Way and fail by not getting a 4 year full scholarship, then you will likely get a few smaller scholarships. Scholarships that aren’t “full” won’t help you all that much due to the scale of costs, but you might be able to pay for shampoo and soap while at school with them. I wouldn’t count on it, but if you can get it, every shampoo bottle is worth it.

When you fail The Hard Way, you will fall back on The Risky Way. This may actually be a good path for you to go, because having tried the hard way means that you spent a lot of time learning, and state schools will likely be easy for you to get into, and succeeding at those schools should not be terribly difficult.

You may get into a high prestige school, but not get a 4 year scholarship. This will be a difficult road for you, because the high prestige school will be hard enough without being borderline for academic excellence already. You may discover that you don’t have the background to succeed at the high prestige school, and then you’ll also accrue vast amounts of debt while failing out. This is a very scary place to get yourself into.

If you get into a high prestige school, I would strongly recommend taking a deferred year of enrollment before going to the high prestige school. If you can get some additional training that will prepare you, such as working at an internship in your major, that would really be ideal. You will probably not have the contacts for it though - I know I had none like that. Even working a minimum wage job for that year is a better option than just jumping in to such a risky education experience. The year off will provide you with an extra year of maturity over your classmates, and also be a constant reminder that you could have been stuck at that job every time you get overwhelmed with your coursework.

Picking a Major

“I just don’t think you would be well-suited to it.”

That was the response that I got when I first voiced my growing sentiment that I wanted to be a programmer. I don’t know if I knew myself well enough at the time to realize that statement would end up cementing my future.

Truthfully, I was a terrible computer scientist for years. I just didn’t have the mindset for it yet. When an error would spit out from my terminal, I had no sense of whether it was a real error or something to be ignored, much less whether it was my fault or how it might be fixed. But after a steady chorus of RTFM and a healthy helping of good old “telling me what to type”, I finally started getting the idea.

The kind of thinking that you do when programming is not the kind where you can get away with sloppiness. Laziness, sure. But you have to ask questions, and attack problems carefully, one step at a time. You have to learn to isolate problems and test your hypotheses.

Not only that, you also need to just know the machine, which means putting in the time at the machine.

I did put in the time, in the long run. My fascination with the machine led me to put a massive amount of hours into tweaking Linux, recompiling my drivers to get this or that working, extolling its values to friends and family, and installing it wherever I could.

So when someone tells you that they think you aren’t suited to something, I hope you will say, “Not yet, but I’m working on it.”

Finding Your Depth

Admitting you are out of your depth is one of the most treacherous grounds you will tread. In a certain sense, most intelligent people spend most of their time operating outside of their body of known materiel. This is because they tend to get bored retreading old ground.

Some people are more comfortable with it than others. Some people don’t even seem to notice they are way outside their knowledge pool. And, occasionally, that can be a good thing, because the world is big, and knowing how much others know that you have no idea of is a massively ego-shrinking experience, and some folks run their gas tank on ego.

When you don’t know how much you don’t know, you don’t realize that others have already run the experiment you are running, or built the program you are writing, and that is actually a good thing for students. Everyone wants to feel like they have done something important and useful and taking the time to write that already-written program may grant you the experience to later write a program that no one else has thought up yet. Maintaining that sense of discovery and pure Maker joy is one of the tricks really excellent teachers will work hard to cultivate for you.

I remember one of the projects my first year at Olin was to design a set of apparatus that trundled a container of rice up a ramp using a 2 liter bottle of water. I was super ecstatic about designing a new and more efficient water wheel to do this. I thought that I could optimize the spokes on the wheel to be shaped in such a way that it would be super efficient. I spent hours in the cad software we were using and with some experimental software trying to come up with something. I learned a lot about both pieces of software, but in the end a water wheel is a stupidly inefficient way to transport water.

As a student though, it is all about what you can learn on the journey to the answer, not just what the answer actually is. So I still consider the experience to have been valuable even if all we had at the end was an ugly piece of 3D printed plastic that was probably the worst rice ramp in the room.

How do you know then, when you are too far out of your depth? I think it is about listening to your mental gears. If you are trying to get stuff done but finding yourself stuck in park all the time, it may be time to seek out some assistance. It may be that your professor can provide you with the few vital pieces of information you need to get into first gear where you can start making progress again.

Don’t put it off for too long though, if you start having problems. Grinding gears for hours at a time can end up causing mental blocks where you start to believe that you can’t accomplish whatever it is you are trying to do. Your subconscious will likely have no problem coming up with some reason why you ought to be incompetent at partial differential equations, just as an example.

Don’t listen to it. If you are bad at something from the start, just consider it an opportunity to grok whatever it is in far greater detail than other classmates.

Winning At Working

One of the things I never mastered until after college was figuring out how to win at my work environment setup. There’s a lot of things that have to come together to really get a place to study running smoothly, and I think it takes an exceptional amount of self-awareness to be able to call it when one part or another isn’t working out.

The success of your work environment is deeply tied into your emotional state so putting yourself into the state you need should be your primary goal when you manipulate your environment. Pay attention to how the things in your environment affect your mental gearing and do some elimination testing to pick what things can be in or out of that environment.

For me, I find that music is good for programming but bad for memorizing things. I find I need a clean environment, that isn’t too dark, and strongly prefer one with a view of the outdoors where I can gaze (or stare!) when thinking.

The state of the computer matters too. I can usually get away with and or get value from leaving messaging open if I’m performing asynchronous short programming chores, but not if I’m doing something serial like reading a long text.

One of the things that I finally mastered, that has helped me be far more productive, is learning how to manage rabbit holes. Figuring out how to pick out only one small part of the problem and solving just that goes a long way to getting the big goals done. Sometimes you just have to decide which parts on the problem are for tomorrow, and not worry about them until you’ve finished the parts you do know how to do. Often times you’ll find that either the answer becomes obvious when you finish the other parts, or that you don’t really need to interact with the auxiliary issues anyway. Especially if you are just beginning your studies in a field, the vastness of your tasks often can seem overwhelming, and letting the great unknown keep you from getting started will just mean you never get busy.

Romance

I’d love to tell you to just avoid romance altogether in college, but in good conscience I just can’t do that. There never is a good time in your life to have a failed romance, and often there isn’t time for a successful romance. But the simple fact of the matter is that humans, and especially twenty-somethings, are walking bags of hormones waiting to be unleashed. Once you get a puncture, that tire is blowing, and attempting to ignore if will just make your road that much rockier in the long run.

I learned this the very hard way. In my first semester at Olin I fell for a particular colleague, we’ll call him Jim, quite hard. In retrospect it should have been obvious that this was highly likely from the get-go given that the gender counts were perfectly balanced and all of us geeky young engineers were finding others who understood us, and that we could grant a lot of respect to, in very close confines. You could think of it much like a wartime situation, where we were all in the trenches doing our jobs and finding others doing them in often extremely admirable ways.

For me, I had been extremely focused on education prior to this point. The notion that a member of the opposite sex could affect my life in any appreciable way was alien to me. So when I started acting like an idiot with a crush for what was, basically, the first time, I was quite baffled by this development. And when my crush told me he wasn’t interested I responded by saying that that was fine then, and honestly expected nothing more of it.

Anyone with more romantic experience than a rock would probably realize that was a doomed expectation for the end of a first crush, when said crush is in close physical proximity on a regular basis. So I acted erratically and mangled much of the emotional experience of my first year at college.

The particular level of insanity of this situation was far from being caused only by a simple crush. There was a lot going on in my life, from ditching my family religion, ditching my parents, and simultaneously uncovering the hard fact that I was vastly underprepared for the academic rigor I was facing. In addition, I was discovering popular music for the first time, and hadn’t learned to regulate the emotional experiences much of pop can generate.

I think my point still stands though. Romantic involvements can be wonderful, but they can also be terribly messy and hard. My best advice for anyone who hasn’t had their first romantic experience yet is to do it before college, but if you can’t, just try and be prepared for the fact that it might end up causing a lot more emotional turbulence than the flight attendant mentioned. Give yourself the time and attention you need to work through your shit, then work to focus back on what direction you want to take your life in.